Vítor Nascimento Lourenço

Rua Dom Bosco, 89. Apt. 1306, 24220390 Niterói (Brazil)

☐ +55 21 99817 2109 • ☑ vitornaslourenco@gmail.com http://lattes.cnpg.br/7172413417236996

In a Nutshell

I am currently a master's candidate in Computing at the Computing Institute of Federal Fluminense University (IC/UFF), I hold a Bachelor in Computer Science from the same Institute and a Certificate in Entrepreneurship and Innovation from the same University. Also, I am a Computer Technician from the Federal Center for Technological Education Celso Suckow da Fonseca (CEFET/RJ).

My research interests are related to Machine Learning, Applied Artificial Intelligence, Pattern Recognition, Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery, and Information Retrieval.

Work Experience

IBM Research Rio de Janeiro

Research Intern August 2018-present

I support the development of learning-based solutions on knowledge engineering for natural resource challenges. I develop the Python framework for IBM Hyperlinked Knowledge Graph technologies.

LDSOFT

Research Intern July 2017-July 2018

I was responsible the coordination of a project for the development of a trademark image retrieval system using computer vision and pattern recognition techniques. Also, I was member of the development team of a natural language processing system for trademark name matching.

Education

Academic Qualifications.....

Master in Computing Niterói

Federal Fluminense University

2019-Present

· 2019-Present: National Council for Scientific and Technological Development Fellow

· 2019-Present: Student member of Database Research Group

from the Systems and Information Engineering Lab

Bachelor in Computer Science

Niterói Federal Fluminense University 2014-2018

· 2014-2018: Student member of Database Research Group

from the Systems and Information Engineering Lab

· 2014-2016: Founder and leader of Data Science Club - UFF

Minor - Entrepreneurship and Innovation

Niterói Federal Fluminense University 2014-2015

Informatics Technician Rio de Janeiro Federal Center for Technological Education of Rio de Janeiro 2011-2014

· 2012-2014: Student member of Applied Computing Research Group

Languages

Portuguese

🖰 Fluent - Native

English

Advanced - Understanding, reading, writing and speaking

German

Basic - Understanding, reading and writing

Selected Publications.....

- o Moreno, M.; **Lourenço, V.**; Sandro Fiorini S. R.; Costa, P., Brandão, R.; Civitarese, D.; Cerqueira, R.. *Managing Machine Learning Workflow Components*, To appear in the 2020 14th IEEE International Conference on Semantic Computing (ICSC).
- o Souza, R.; Azevedo, L.; Lourenço, V.; Soares, E.; Thiago, R.; Brandão, R.; Civitarese, D.; Brazil, E. V.; Moreno, M.; Valduriez, P.; Mattoso, M.; Cerqueira, R.; Netto, M. A. S.. Provenance Data in the Machine Learning Lifecycle in Computational Science and Engineering. In 2019 14th Workflows in Support of Large-scale Science (WORKS) co-located with the 2019 ACM/IEEE International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis (SC).
- Lourenço, V. N.; Silva, G.G.; Fernandes, L.A.F.. Hierarchy-of-Visual-Words: a Learning-based Approach for Trademark Image Retrieval. In 2019 32nd Conference on Graphics, Patterns and Images (SIBGRAPI), 218-225.
 - Best Computer Vision/Image Processing/Pattern Recognition Main Track Paper Award
 - Best Work Award in the Workshop of Undergraduate Works
- Lourenço, V.; Mann, P.; Guimarães, A.; Paes, A.; Oliveira, D.. Towards Safer (Smart) Cities: Discovering
 Urban Crime Patterns Using Logic-based Relational Machine Learning. In 2018 International Joint
 Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN), 1-8.
- Lourenço, V.; Mann, P.; Paes, A.; Oliveira, D.. SiAPP: Um Sistema para Análise de Ocorrências de Crimes Baseado em Aprendizado Lógico-Relacional. In 2016 XII Brazilian Symposium on Information Systems (SBSI), 168-175.

Technical skills

Programming Languages

Advanced knowledges in C, Python and TeX; Basic knowledges in R and Java.

Data Science and Machine Learning Tools

Advanced knowledge in NumPy, SciPy, Matplotlib, and Scikit-Learn; Basic knowledge in Pandas, Tensorflow, OpenCV, and Airflow.